#### CURRICULUM VITAE

# Jeffrey Hanson

CIBIO/InBIO, Centro de Investigação em Biodiversidade e Recursos Genéticos da Universidade do Porto, Vairão, Portugal

☑ jeffrey.hanson@uqconnect.edu.au 🧸 jeffrey-hanson.com

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research concerns the challenges involved in conserving biodiversity. I am interested in understanding how areas can be managed to achieve conservation objectives for minimal cost. In particular, I specialize in operationalizing ecological and evolutionary processes to develop plans for protected area systems that maximize the long-term persistence of biodiversity.

### **EDUCATION**

- 2013–2018 PhD, Biology, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Richard Fuller and Jonathon Rhodes, thesis: Conserving evolutionary processes.)
- 2011–2012 BS (Hons), First Class, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Steve Salisbury, Craig Franklin, Hamish Campbell, and Ross Dwyer, thesis: *Using stable isotopes to assess the relationship between body-size, habitat use and diet in estuarine crocodiles (Crocodylus porosus)*)
- 2007–2010 BS, Major in Ecology, The University of Queensland, Australia

# PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS

- 2012–2013 Research Assistant to Richard Fuller, The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2012–2013 Research Assistant to Jonathon Rhodes, The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2012 Casual Professional Staff, The School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, Australia

### **EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES**

Classroom Instruction, The University of Queensland, Australia

2013–2015 Professional tutor to the "Field Ecology" course, coordinated by Myron Zalucki

### Workshop Instruction

- 2017 Use of Machine Learning in Conservation, Moving beyond just Maxent and SDMs coordinated by Falk Huettmann at the 28th International Congress for Conservation Biology (ICCB), Cartagena, Colombia.
- 2015 Geospatial Analysis in R coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer, Rebbecca Runting and Jutta Beher at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.
  - Smoothing the Marxan Flow with R coordinated by Matthew Watts at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.
- 2013 Introduction to Geospatial Analysis coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.
  - Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis in R workshop coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2011 Introducing R coordinated by Simon Blomberg at The University of Queensland, Australia.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Journal articles

- Hanson JO, Fuller RA, & Rhodes JR (2019) Conventional methods for enhancing connectivity in conservation planning do not always maintain gene flow. *Journal of Applied Ecology*, 56: 913–922.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP & Fuller RA (2018) raptr: Representative and Adequate Prioritization Toolkit in R. Methods in Ecology & Evolution, 9: 320–330.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Riginos C & Fuller RA (2017) Environmental and geographic variables are effective surrogates for genetic variation in conservation planning. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 114: 12755–12760.

Mather AT, **Hanson JO**, Pope LC & Riginos C (2017) Comparative phylogeography of two co-distributed but ecologically distinct rainbowfishes of far-northern Australia. *Journal of Biogeography*, 45: 127–141.

Dhanjal-Adams KL, **Hanson JO**, Murray NJ, Phinn SR, Wingate VR, Mustin K, Lee JR, Allan JR, Cappadonna JL, Studds CE, Clemens RS, Roelfsema CM & Fuller RA (2016) Distribution and protection of intertidal habitats in Australia. *Emu* **116**: 208–214.

Dudaniec RY, Worthington Wilmer J, **Hanson JO**, Warren M, Bell S & Rhodes JR (2016) Dealing with uncertainty in landscape genetic resistance models: a case of three co-occurring marsupials. *Molecular Ecology*, **25**: 470–486.

Auerbach NA, Wilson KA, Tulloch AI, Rhodes JR, **Hanson JO** & Possingham HP (2015) Effects of threat management interactions on conservation priorities. Conservation Biology, **29**: 1626–1635.

Bunton JD, Ernst AT, **Hanson JO**, Beyer HL, Hammill E, Runge CA, Venter O, Possingham HP & Rhodes JR (2015) Integrated planning of linear infrastructure and conservation offsets. In Weber, T, McPhee, MJ & Andersson RS (eds) *MODSIM* 2015, 21st International Congress on Modelling and Simulation. Modelling and Simulation Society of Australia and New Zealand, December 2015, pp. 1427–1433.

**Hanson JO**, Salisbury SW, Campbell HA, Dwyer RG, Jardine TD & Franklin CE (2015) Feeding across the food web: the interaction between diet, movement and body size in estuarine crocodiles (*Crocodylus porosus*). *Austral Ecology*, **40**: 275–286.

Rabeb D, Othman DS, Essilfie AT, Hansbro PM, **Hanson JO**, McEwan AG & Kappler U (2015) Maturation of molybdoenzymes and its influence on the pathogenesis of non-typeable *Haemophilus* influenzae. *Frontiers in Microbiology*, **6**: 01219.

Runge CA, Watson JEM, Butchart HM, **Hanson JO**, Possingham HP & Fuller RA (2015) Protected areas and global conservation of migratory birds. *Science*, **350**: 1255–1258.

Popular science articles

Beher J & **Hanson JO** (2015) Welcome to the Mapotron. *Decision Point*, **86**: 10–11.

### PEER REVIEW ACTIVITIES

I have reviewed submissions to following journals: Austral Ecology, Conservation Letters, Diversity and Distributions, Global Change Biology, and PLoS ONE.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

### Conference presentations

- Hanson JO, Schuster R, Morrell N, Strimas-Mackey M, Watts ME, Arcese P, Bennett JR, Possingham HP (2018) prioritizr: Systematic conservation prioritization in R. Oral presentation to UseR! 2018, Brisbane, Australia.
- 2016 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP, Fuller RA (2016) RAPR: Representative and Adequate Prioritizations in R. Oral presentation to Society for Conservation Biology 4th Oceania Congress, Brisbane, Australia.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Fuller RA (2014) Conservation planning for intra-specific biodiversity using surrogates. Oral presentation to the Meeting of the Minds miniconference at The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia.

#### **Seminars**

- 2017 Systematic conservation prioritization in R presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2016 Biodiversity processes in reserve-selection presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.

#### Scientific meetings and networking events

- 2018 rOpenSci Unconference, Melbourne, Australia.
- 2017 R Unconference hosted by the Brisbane Users of R Group, Brisbane, Australia.
- 2016 rOpenSci Unconference, Brisbane, Australia.

### SELECTED PROJECTS

An R package for generating spatial prioritizations that capture within feature variation (e.g. intra-specific genetic variation). Available at https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=raptr.

prioritizr An R package for designing and solving conservation planning problems. Available at https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=prioritizr.

# SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

- Compute resource allocation by the National eResearch Collaboration Tools and Resources (NeCTAR) project (2017)
- Postgraduate Travel Award Scholarship, The School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, Australia (2016)
- Australian Postgraduate Award (APA) Scholarship (2013)